"Stay calm."
Do that, nothing can go wrong.
Got it?
Yeah, we got it.
Hi, good to see you again.
Uh, yes, that time of the year.
I have to get my shoes resoled.
- Uh, put. Put.
- Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Right there.
Got just a... a hole there.
Everybody, get down!
This is a robbery!
Get out from behind the counter.
Get out here! Now!
Get down!
Down!
Get down on the ground!
Nobody do anything stupid!
Cameras. Move.
I wanna cell phones kicked into
the center of the room right now.
Let's see 'em!
- Name.
- Still Jane.
Thank you.
And, uh...
how long do you think
that'll be?
We'll see.
Okay.
Good to see you, too.
Everybody's gonna go home
to their families
if they don't do
anything stupid.
Who here can open the vault?
I can. I can.
Get up! Get in the back!
Get the bags.
Go!
Open it.
Hey. Kill it.
Here. Fill it.
Fill it.
What's taking him so long?
We don't need these.
Count to a hundred.
One
two
three...
What the hell was that?
Let's go!
Back up, come on.
"Hey, you idiot! You hit my car!"
There's a cop.
I think you need a little lie-down.
Just have a little rest here.
- I think I might faint.
- Okay. There we go.
Just put your head down there.
Okay. Thanks.
Three men hit the vault
in the back for a million in cash.
They shot killed
an assistant manager.
Any witnesses?
Lots, but they're not much help.
The robbers were wearing masks.
They also blacked out
the cameras with spray paint
but I'm pulling the footage.
- Where's Jane?
- Inside.
- Is that a friend of the victim?
- Fiancée.
Works in the bank.
Hey.
Nice shoes.
Uh, yes, uh, loaners.
Mine are in getting repaired.
How long is that gonna take?
We'll see. The, uh...
cobbler fainted.
Are you coming?
Meh.
It's a little cramped in there.
No expended casings in here.
Any outside?
Found 2. Both 9 millimeter.
Witnesses say six shots
were fired outside
so one of the shooters
must've been using a revolver.
Let me know what the M.E. says
when he pulls the slug from the victim.
- You got anything?
- Maybe.
I just spoke
with a SAC P.D. detective
who thinks
this robbery's connected
with three others committed
in the past six months.
In all of them, two, sometimes
three masked men
took out the security cameras,
passed up the teller drawers
and went straight for the vault,
just like these guys.
How many victims
in the other robberies?
None. He's the first.
Did SAC P.D. finish
their search of the bank?
Almost. Nothing so far.
Okay. Here's how
we're gonna run this.
You coordinate the witness interviews
and tell Rigsby to pull the case files
from the other robberies.
- I wanna know if this is the same guys.
- All right.
- This is Lisbon.
- Cho.
Was the safe deposit vault
open when you got here?
Yeah. Why?
Just curious.
Yes, sir.
I will be right there.
That was Bertram.
I gotta go.
Bank robberies belong
to the FBI.
This case is ours.
And tell me, why does the CBI
continue to encroach
on our jurisdiction?
We were on site first.
It's not our fault
if you're late off the mark.
Agent Lisbon, Agent Mancini
has a valid point
- regarding jurisdiction.
- Thank you.
Sir, the crime my team and I
are investigating
is a crime of murder.
A murder committed
during a bank robbery.
The murder supersedes
the crime of armed robbery.
So our investigation
takes priority.
You're more than welcome
to investigate
after we close the murder.
- Assuming you do.
- You know what they say
- about assuming things. It makes--
- I know exactly what--
All right. That's enough.
Agent Mancini, Agent Lisbon
and her team will take point
in the murder investigation.
In the meantime, you will have
full access to all case files.
Agreed?
Hey.
- We have a personal problem?
- Personal problem?
You act like you don't like me
like I killed your pet tortoise
or something.
What, are we in high school?
You lost the most important witness
we've ever had in the Red John case
and now you wonder why
I won't make nice?
I didn't lose Lorelei Martins and I want her
back just as badly as you do.
And generally speaking
when people act like
they don't like me
it's because they really do.
- They just don't wanna admit it.
- Yeah. No.
I don't like you.
You'll have the case files
by the end of the day.
Listen, there's this poker game
we got going on.
It's a friendly game,
mostly law enforcement
State Department, FBI.
You want in?
Maybe. When?
I'll call you with the details.
Good luck with the case.
Hope you find your man.
All right.
You boys leave tonight.
Don't come back.
I don't wanna see you again.
Understood?
Well, that was a complete
waste of time.
Not one security camera near
SAC Federal caught the robbery.
- Thanks.
- Sure. What's all this?
Case files and footage
from the other robberies.
Check this out.
The SAC Fed job
was by far the largest haul--
more than double
any of the other robberies.
- They're getting ambitious.
- Not they. He.
Now in each one of the robberies,
there's maybe 30 seconds of footage
before the cameras were blacked out.
That was enough to analyze
the suspects' height, weight
build, and skin color, so I did.
And guess what.
Only one of the robbers
was involved in all four crimes.
That's him.
So the other robbers--
they were work for hire?
Exactly. They do one job
and then they disappear.
But if we can find this guy
we find them all.
He's the key.
Do you remember anything
about the men who did this?
No. Not a thing.
You know Ernie and I were up
for the same promotion?
I was mad when I didn't get it.
But not now.
That could've been me
in there.
Ernie was a good man.
He didn't deserve this.
What were you doing
during the robbery?
What they told me to.
I am not trying to get shot
over this job.
Ernie must've done something wrong.
Poor fool.
And that's when the robbers
ordered you to the ground?
Yeah. He stuck a gun
right in my face.
I was gonna grab it
and take those guys down
but I just had back surgery
so I didn't wanna risk
the loss of innocent lives.
After that, one of the robbers
took assistant manager
Ernie Wright into the vault.
I think so. I don't really know.
I was in the back.
During the robbery?
In the men's room.
Is this really necessary?
- I've already been through--
- You were in the men's room
the whole time?
Yes.
I was, uh, washing up
when I heard the gunshot.
Of course, I didn't know it was
a gunshot at the time.
It wasn't until I stepped into the hall
that I heard the screaming.
Was anyone back there
with you?
Not that I saw.
Ernie and I had lunch plans.
We were just about to leave
when I went into the back
to use the restroom.
Yes, we saw as much
on the security footage.
We also saw your manager,
Armin Gagnon
heading into the men's room
just behind you.
- Do you remember seeing him?
- No.
Not until after I heard the shot.
I opened the door,
and Armin was standing there.
Then I heard the robbers shouting,
so I closed the door
and I-I hid in the stall
until they left.
Mr. Gagnon was in the hallway?
- Here?
- Yes.
Why?
Just trying to get the facts
straight, ma'am.
Was Ernie the type to fight back?
No.
Ernie was a big Teddy bear.
He'd never fight unless it was
to protect someone he loved.
Hey. How's it going?
- I think I got it.
- Okay. Lay it on me.
This ringleader--
he had to have planned
the robberies, right?
Right.
Which means he probably
visited each of the banks
before he robbed them.
On camera and without a mask, yeah.
So we run all the security footage
through facial recognition software
and when we find the man that visited
all four banks before the robberies
- we find our ringleader.
- Great idea.
It's an idea.
I don't know if I'd call it great.
Ah, he's just jealous.
- What are you wearing?
- Oh, these things?
Ah, they're loaners.
How about this?
Whoever figures out
the bank robber's name first
wins lunch for a week.
Yeah, that usually
doesn't end well for us.
What do you say, Grace?
You feeling lucky?
You're on.
Yeah.
"It was closed."
You're certain?
Must've been closed.
The safe deposit vault
is always closed.
- I think it was closed.
- Yeah.
I want you to close your eyes.
Hey, we're grown-ups.
Come on.
Now put your mental self
back in this very spot
in that very moment.
I want you to hear the sound
that your shoes made
on this marble floor.
Now without opening your eyes
I want you to picture the door
as you pass by.
Can you do that?
Can you see the door?
- Yes.
- And?
It was open.
Which means someone
went inside the safe deposit
vault during the robbery.
Mostly likely a robber
trying to take something
from a deposit box.
Oh, my. What if they did?
Let's find out, shall we?
- That's impossible.
- It is?
The safe deposit boxes
are legal property
of the individuals who rent them.
We don't even have keys.
Only the owners do.
You wouldn't happen to have a list
of those names, would you?
We got a match.
Oh, good morning to you, too.
The suspect visited
Pacific Bank of Modesto
and Fresno Savings and Loan
a week before each was robbed.
He comes in, cases the place,
then leaves
without making a transaction.
I think we found our guy.
- His name anyway.
- Well, congratulations.
Me, too.
You did? When?
When did you figure it out?
About an hour ago.
Ah, well, there you have it.
I figured it out two hours ago
so it looks like I win the bet.
Okay, what's his name?
Oh, I'm not gonna fall
for that old trick, Grace.
Write it down on a piece of paper
so I know that you're not lying.
John Hutten.
How did you do that?
How did I do it?
Does it matter? I did it.
Rigsby, we got a work address
on the suspect. Let's go.
- Uh, yeah.
- Uh, by the way, Grace
there's a fabulous Thai place
on Sixth Street.
They make a delicious Tom Kha Gai.
Mr. Hutten?
John Hutten?
Put it down.
Let me see your hands.
I'm Agent Lisbon with the CBI.
Just wanna ask you a few questions.
Agent Lisbon, you said?
Pleasure to meet you.
John William Hutten.
You were arrested twice
for grand theft auto.
You served 18 months in Folsom.
Here you are
a suspect in a robbery
and homicide.
Is there a charge
at the end of this, detective?
Where were you yesterday
at noon?
Home. Sick.
Is there anyone
who can verify that?
No, because I was home, sick.
You were caught on camera
at four banks in the Central Valley.
All four of those banks were robbed
within weeks of you visiting.
Which is conclusive evidence
of what?
I think it's evidence
that your client
planned to commit armed robbery.
Then charge him, and we'll see
what a jury has to say.
What were you doing
in those banks?
Times are tight.
I was shopping
for competitive interest rates
in money market accounts.
And you've been smart so far.
Blacking out security cameras,
going straight for the vault.
But this time, you screwed up,
and somebody ended up dead.
Maybe the SAC Fed job
was too big for you.
O-or maybe the murder
was a part of the plan all along.
I didn't rob Sacramento Federal.
I didn't rob any bank.
But if I did, I certainly wouldn't need
to kill someone.
That's just sloppy.
Now I've had my brushes
with the law
but I've learned some things
from them.
Like the fact that you can't use
my past against me in court
and no matter what you say
inside this little room
you have nothing on me.
So unless there's something else,
Agent Lisbon
I think I should be getting
back to work.
We'll see ourselves out.
Hello.
Patrick Jane. I'm working
the robbery-murder case.
We already spoke with Agent Lisbon.
Yes, I know.
I saw the whole thing.
Uh, just a head's-up,
for future reference
that large mirror is,
in fact, a window.
- What do you want?
- Uh, I can see that you're a professional
but, uh, Agent Lisbon was correct.
Uh...
this last robbery
was a break in pattern.
Uh, I don't mean that just
because someone was killed.
I'm talking about the entire job.
How's that?
Well, the other three robberies
were simple--
small town banks,
very little security
straightforward.
But SAC Federal--bigger.
Much bigger.
Mr. Jane, we've already answered.
Now there had to be something
that gave you
that extra bit of confidence
to pull this one off.
- What was that?
- John...
Don't say a word.
You had an inside man.
Yes.
Of course.
I should've known. I used to use one
on occasion in my stage act.
Stage act, huh?
Uh, let me guess-- balloon sculpting?
Animal impressions?
That's it.
John's a good worker.
Shows up on time,
keeps his mouth shut.
Does he hang out
with any of his coworkers?
Not that I've noticed.
Keeps to himself mostly.
Has he been acting strange recently?
Do anything out of the ordinary?
Like come in in a dress?
No. Nothing like that.
Can you confirm whether or not Hutten
was at work on these dates?
I can't help you.
These are all before
John started working here.
The last few days--
Hutten called in sick?
Yeah, he said he had some
kind of bug. Couldn't get outta bed.
You believe him?
Sure. Why wouldn't I?
It's been going around.
What do you mean by that?
Two of my other guys
got the same thing.
Arroyo brothers--
Jorge, Cesar.
We're gonna need
their home address.
When are you getting
your shoes back?
They're not so bad, are they?
Are you sure this is
the right place to do this?
Well, Hutten's inside man
works at the bank and it seems...
Everyone that works at the bank
is here. I'll be right back.
Jane, wait.
W--
- Hello.
Were you friends with my grandson?
Perfect. Glad you're all here.
Quick.
What's your favorite color?
- What?
- Favorite color. Red? Green? Blue?
Blue.
Out of all your employees,
which is the least trustworthy?
What? None of them.
- You. What's your name?
- Casey.
Casey, you work in banking
yet your personal finances
are a wreck.
- No, they're not.
- Oh, please.
That handbag on your salary?
Dead giveaway.
And you bite your nails.
Sure sign of anxiety.
Yet someone as anxious as you
probably doesn't have the stomach
to pull off a crime like this.
Crime? What crime?
You didn't like Ernie, did you?
You felt threatened by him.
- Who told you that?
- You did just now.
Clearly not smart enough
to pull off a robbery.
- What'd you say to me?
- You heard me.
Uh, when I asked your manager
who he trusted the least
his eyes darted to you.
- They did not.
- Repeat after me--
- "I am the inside man."
- Hell, no.
Just as I thought.
Not you either.
Wait.
Th-there was an inside man?
- What's your name?
- Uh, Tai.
Tai. Pleasure to meet you.
Have we met? Did you help rob
Sacramento Federal Bank?
No!
- You sure? Yes?
- Yeah. No!
- No? Yes?
- Get off me.
This--this is
completely inappropriate.
Show Ernie some respect.
Ernie.
Yes. Ernie.
Absolutely right.
My apologies.
That was 1982?
Yeah.
Jane. Jane, where you going?
I just have to check on something.
I'll be right back.
- No.
- You know, you should probably answer that.
- It's very important.
- Damn it, Jane.
- Hello?
- "Hey, boss."
We checked out
the Arroyo brothers' apartment.
Place is empty.
According to the building manager
they took off late last night.
Any word
on where they were going?
No forwarding address
but they told the manager
they were headed to Mexico
to visit family.
And we also tracked down the van
that was used in the robbery.
It was torched pretty bad.
Yeah, it doesn't look like
we're gonna get anything form it.
All right. Flag the Arroyo brothers
with customs.
If they're on their way to Mexico
maybe we can get them
before they cross the border.
All right.
Uh, Lisbon.
Found something.
You will never believe who was working
with the bank robbers.
Ernie Wright.
Probably shouldn't discuss it here.
We're very sorry for your loss.
There's no way Ernie could do
something like this.
There's just no way.
We found a one-way ticket
to Brazil in Ernie's name.
No.
No. That's absurd.
Ernie?
Robbing a bank?
I mean, he wasn't the type.
He was exactly the type.
Judging from these photographs here
I'd say Ernie
became a different man.
Yeah, he lost weight
started dressing sharper.
Powerful external transformations
can often coincide
with even larger internal ones.
He was trying to better himself.
Why? Because of you?
I encouraged him, of course.
I loved him.
Ernie was just a teller
when we met.
He was still living at home.
Shy, inexperienced with women?
Yes.
And what changed?
He finished his degree
got promoted to assistant manager
and bought this house.
And you were by his side
every step of the way.
You must have seen something
very special in Ernie.
Yes.
I saw that he was sweet
and how good a man he was.
He could never do something
like this.
No way.
Where'd you grow up?
Upstate New York.
A town called Newburgh.
And you two?
Uh, Chicago.
Here.
In Sacramento. Why?
No reason.
So if we prove Hutten's connection
to Ernie
we prove Hutten's guilt.
But a connection
should've come up by now.
How did Hutten know Ernie?
- Hot reading.
- What?
Well, Hutten's a careful,
meticulous professional.
He wouldn't have used an inside man
that could be traced back to him.
So he researched
the staff at the bank.
Hot reading.
Very easy to do these days.
And he kept digging until he found
someone with shaky ethics
and a yen for a better life--
Ernie.
Wow. It's late.
What are you still doing here?
Trying to find a connection
between Hutten and Ernie Wright.
I've checked Ernie's e-mail account
text messages,
and cell phone records.
Nothing. So far there's no sign
of communication between them.
Sorry to hear it.
Oh, listen, uh, the bank
manager's supposed to send out
a list of safety deposit box owners.
Right. It's on my desk.
Thank you very much.
Silly me. Almost forgot.
I've really been craving
Italian lately
so what do you say we get a nice linguine
for lunch tomorrow?
- Okay?
- Yeah. Okay.
Ciao. Ciao.
Jane.
- Jane, wake up.
- Yeah.
- What's the time?
- 8:00.
- Oh, we have to get going.
- Where?
I'll explain it all in the car.
No. You'll explain it now, please.
Oh, I like it when you get
all authoritarian on me.
- Talk. Where are we going?
- To catch Ernie's killer.
How? We don't have anything
on Hutten.
Hutten didn't kill Ernie.
He didn't?
Well, he robbed the bank,
all right
but he was telling the truth
when he said he didn't need
to shoot anyone.
Why would he do that?
It's sloppy, not his style.
Jane, I need more than that.
You remember the safe deposit vault
was open during the robbery?
I just assumed that someone took
something from there
but, uh, I got it all backwards.
They didn't take anything.
They put something in there.
What?
You really want me to tell you?
It's gonna ruin the surprise.
- Yes. I don't like surprises.
- Three guesses then.
I'll give you a hint.
It's--it's not animal
or vegetable.
You know, we can't open a safe deposit
box without a warrant.
We can if we have
the owner's permission.
Uh, we don't open
for a half-hour.
Is everything all right?
Everything's fine.
We just want to ask your employees
some questions.
It shouldn't take long.
Can you have everyone who was here
at the time of the robbery
gather in the safe deposit vault,
yourself included?
Yes, absolutely.
Has there been a break in the case?
You'll see.
What's this all about?
Oh, I've gathered you here
to help catch Ernie's killer.
How are we gonna catch
the bank robber?
Well, the bank robber
didn't kill Ernie.
- Then who did?
- Uh, one of you.
- What?
- I don't think so, buddy.
- I would never hurt Ernie.
- Whoa. There's no need for objections.
One of you shot Ernie
during the robbery
and you hid the gun
in a safe deposit box.
- I am sure of it.
- But that--
Yes, exactly, Doug.
That means the killer would've had
to have planned the murder
a long way in advance
so one of you,
who I will identify shortly
is a cold-blooded schemer.
Now first of all
if there's anyone here
that feels the urge to leave feel free.
Please do so. But know this--
we will assume you are our killer.
Armin, if you wouldn't mind
unlocking the vault door.
Thank you.
Before we begin
uh, Agent Lisbon has a few words.
Agent Lisbon?
I've been authorized
by the district attorney's office
to offer Ernie's killer a plea deal.
Ten years in prison
if you cooperate now
and open the deposit box.
Ten years.
That's a very generous offer.
And all you have to do
is open the box
before I'm forced to.
Just as I'd hoped.
Here.
Definitely somewhere here.
You sure?
Positive.
The offer is now 15 years.
All right, this is absurd.
You can't play some game
with people's lives.
Armin, we're the law.
We can do whatever we want.
Any takers for 15 years?
Very well.
Mm, not really feeling it.
Yes.
It's somewhere in this group here.
The offer is now 20 years.
20 years right now.
There it is.
Your last chance of seeing freedom
in your lifetime.
All you need is a little key
that fits in a little lock.
Suit yourselves.
I believe...
It's one of these three here.
Starting on five.
Uh, Stephens
Hudson, Keene.
- Stephens, Hudson, Keene.
- 25 years.
If we have to force open
the box, the deal's off.
You'll be facing
first-degree murder
and the district attorney
will aggressively pursue
the death penalty.
You might get life if you're lucky.
- All right, Jane. Which one is it?
- Yeah. Yeah. Uh, Stephens...
No. No.
Keene?
No, I don't think so.
- Perhaps it's Hudson.
- Wait.
Nancy?
- I knew it.
- Oh, my God. You evil bitch!
There's no need for that.
Let's see if the key fits.
Shall we?
Nancy Sterling, you're under arrest
for the murder of Ernie Wright.
Turn around. Put your hands
behind your back.
When I met Ernie, he was a loser.
Fat, stuck in his job,
still living with his parents.
And you helped him change?
Helped him?
I made him the man he was.
I supported him
when he went back to school
found him his house
I even helped him get promoted.
And how did he repay me?
He completely lost interest
in me.
And you resented him for it.
You're damn right I did.
I thought he was cheating on me.
He was getting in shape
working out.
Don't think I didn't notice
other women looking at him.
"You should've seen Ernie."
"He loved it."
Is that when you began
spying on him?
I checked his phone, his e-mail.
One time I followed him
into one of those Internet cafes.
So shady.
He was using a secret e-mail account.
Which you hacked into.
That's when I found the e-mails.
And you're referring to the correspondence
between Ernie and John Hutten, right?
More like step-by-step details
outlining how they were gonna rob
the bank.
I didn't know what to do.
But then I found
that ticket to Brazil.
Ernie was gonna leave me.
Me, after everything
I'd done for him.
I don't think so.
"I had the details for the robbery."
"I knew exactly where everyone
was going to be"
"and when they were
going to be there."
"So I hid."
"And I waited
for the robbers to leave."
"Then went into the cash vault."
"Ernie never suspected
a thing."
- "I'm keeping the ring."
- "What are you--"
"You should've seen the look
on his face."
"It was perfect."
"Except for one thing."
"I left the safe deposit vault door open."
"When I tried to go back
and close it"
"it was too late."
You know, you could've
just called the police.
- Turned Ernie in.
- I thought about that.
I really did.
But Ernie was gonna leave me.
Me.
I was planning our wedding
and he was just
gonna disappear forever.
He deserved everything he got.
This is getting to be grounds
for harassment, Agent Lisbon.
I told him this wouldn't take long.
"I will arrive Tuesday
at 12:00 p.m. exactly."
"You will be in the lobby."
"I will take you in
back at gunpoint"
"where you will open the vault."
"You will help load the cash
into duffel bags"
"then you will stay behind."
Ernie's fiancée was spying on him.
Text messages, phone calls.
She even found the secret e-mail account
that he was using.
As a matter of fact, she saved
every e-mail you sent him.
You ready to talk
about that deal now?
Hutten wasn't the killer so it had
to be somebody else in the bank
but why Nancy?
Whoever killed Ernie had to have known
about the robbery in advance.
Well, Nancy was, uh,
the likely candidate.
- She's also a classic power dater.
- A what?
Oh, you know the type.
They date down so they have
all the power in a relationship.
Oh.
And how did you know this?
Uh, well, she had more than half
of the space in Ernie's closet.
I mean, she didn't even live there
and she had more than half
of his closet space?
And how did you know which
safe deposit box was Nancy's?
I hot read her.
I had the list of owners
and the bank staff files.
I knew one of the names
had to be Nancy in disguise.
Hudson?
No one ever strays very far
when it comes to false names.
Nancy said that she grew up in
a small town in upstate New York--
- Newburgh.
- On the Hudson River.
On the Hudson River.
You know, these shoes are actually
quite comfortable.
They're growing on me.
- Not on me.
- No?
Oh, hey, Teresa.
Glad you made it.
It's a pretty high-class crowd.
I wish you would've warned me.
Nah. They're pussycats.
Come on. I'll introduce you.
Teresa Lisbon, this is district attorney
- Don Wolcott.
- Hi.
- FBI Bureau Director, Charles Bailey...
- Sir.
- Senator Eileen Dawkins.
- State Senator.
Here. Have a seat.
Get you a drink?
Yeah. Can I have a scotch
on the rocks, please?
You got it.
- Oh, I think you know this guy, right?
- Teresa.
I didn't take you for a gambler.
Oh, it's not gambling
if you know you're gonna win.
Well, we got a live one.
Watch out.
Look at that, huh?
Beautiful work.
- Yeah.
- Thank you.
Okay. Here.
There we go.
For the rental.
Thank you. Good night, Mr. Jane.
- Good night.
- Good night, Niko.
I'm headed home.
I'll see you tomorrow.
Uh, yeah, tomorrow--
curry, definitely.
I feel like some Indian.
You gotta tell me. How did
you come up with Hutten's name?
It's driving me crazy.
Fair enough.
Get a pen and some paper.
Write down a name, any name.
Wayne Rigsby.
You guessed?
No. Although with that name,
it wouldn't be hard to.
I, uh, read your pen.
- So you cheated?
- That's a dirty word.
Maybe just a little.
Well, here's what I think
of your little trick.
I didn't quite get the first word
but the second word was
definitely "you".
Good night.
Oh, well, that's not very nice.